Guide to the Maggie Hopp Photographs 1978-2010, 2020 PR 342
New-York Historical Society
Maggie Hopp photographs
1978-2010, 2020
New-York Historical Society
Hopp, Maggie (Margaret), 1945-
PR 342
33.5 Linear feet in 28 boxes
The collection includes photographs by Maggie Hopp (b. 1945), primarily of midtown and lower Manhattan in New York City from the late 1970s to the late 1990s. Many of the images depict the exteriors and interiors of theaters of 42nd Street and Times Square in the 1970s, often in a deteriorated condition, and the demolition or gut renovations of these buildings. Other images include exterior views of venues featuring sexually pornographic entertainment, views of lower and midtown Manhattan along the Hudson River waterfront, along 6th Avenue (Avenue of the Americas), of Creative Time's 42nd Street Art Project of 1993-94, of the Luxor Baths, and of other aspects of the built environment at a transitional moment in New York's real estate development.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes an extensive number of photographs by Maggie Hopp, referred to collectively by her as the New York City Archive. The collection holds about 2,000 photographic prints, mostly 8x10 and 11x14 in size, though there are many copies of many of the images. There are also almost 1,000 sheets of contacts, slides, and 35mm negative strips, which include the printed images, but many more as well. The bulk of the photographs range from the late 1970s to late 1990s. Generally, the photographs fall into the following principal categories as labeled by Hopp:
"Waterfront." This set includes images taken along the Hudson River waterfront in lower Manhattan, primarily in the mid-1990s before the Hudson River Park was constructed. These images include the interiors and exteriors of warehouses and other buildings (e.g., graffitied trailers, Holland Tunnel air shaft, Marine Aviation Terminal, Department of Docks, Prince Theater on West Street); skyline views (e.g., Empire State Building, World Trade Center, Statue of Liberty); piers and docks (e.g., Chelsea Piers, Pier 57, Pier 64); ships docked or cruising on the Hudson (Intrepid aircraft carrier, USS Edson, Circle Line, Spirit Cruises, Song of America, Robert Fulton, Queen Elizabeth 2, tugboats, commuter boats, etc.); South Street Seaport; Riverside South; Fulton Landing; Hudson River Sculpture Center; Manhattan Golf Club Driving Range; police helicopter; pedestrians, rollerbladers, homeless individuals, and other street life along the riverside walkway; winter scenes; and many more. Many of these photographs were displayed in Hopp's 1997 exhibition On the Waterfront at the Intrepid Sea, Air & Space Museum.
"Outer Smut." Hopp's title refers to the marquees, signage, storefronts, and other exterior views of pornographic movie houses and other adult/sex entertainment venues on 42nd Street. This set includes 16x20 color prints. The prints are dated 1999, though it is likely that the images date from much earlier.
"Theaters Under Siege." This set includes black and white photographs of the exteriors and interiors of 42nd Street theaters. These photographs capture images of the often deteriorated condition of the theaters in the late 1970s, before condemnation by New York state, and trace their evolution through demolition or gut renovation into the late 1990s. Among the theaters depicted are the New Amsterdam, Victory, Lyric, Liberty, Selwyn, and Henry Miller's. This set includes the photographs and installation views of Hopp's 1990 exhibition at the Municipal Art Society concerning the New Amsterdam.
Creative Time/42nd Street Art Project. This set includes color and b&w images of the 42nd Street Art Project of 1993 and 1994. Creative Time was formed in 1973 to provide an organization for artists to experiment with ideas and new works for public exhibition in alternative spaces. One of Creative Time's projects was the 42nd Street Art Project (1993, 1994). In the face of New York's plans to renovate and change the character of 42nd Street, Creative Time sought "to address the neighborhood's history through temporary installations in the storefronts, windows, public areas, and on signage between Broadway and Eighth Avenue."
In addition, the collection includes images of various buildings and locations from midtown and lower Manhattan that were subject or potentially subject to development: 6th Avenue (Avenue of the Americas) from about 14th Street north to 30th Street, 4 Times Square, Hotel Diplomat, the Debt Clock, among many others. There is a rich set of photographs, in both color and black and white, of the interior of the Luxor Baths building, demolished in the 1980s. Many photographs include individuals interested in the development of New York's real estate, including Seymour Durst and governors Mario Cuomo and George Pataki. There are also photographs of protests in the 1990s against such development.
The collection also includes Hopp's self-published 2020 book of her photographs of her elderly Aunt Belle, taken in the years shortly before Belle's death in 1989 at age 108.
The container list includes more detail on the content of each box in the collection.
Related Archival Materials Note
N-YHS holds other photograph collections concerning the Times Square area during the 1970s. These include:
Kenneth Siegel Photograph Collection (PR 298)
Andreas Feininger Photograph Collection (PR 207)
Arrangement Note
The collection is generally arranged by subject matter: "Waterfront," "Outer Smut," "Theaters under Siege" and other 42nd Street-related photographs. Materials found toward the close include a variety of subjects.
With minor exceptions, the photographs remain in the boxes and in the order within boxes as originally presented to N-YHS by the photographer/donor. Generally, the headings used in the container list below are the same used by the photographer to label the boxes. [Bracketed] references were added by the processing archivist.
Biographical/Historical Note
Maggie Hopp (b. 1945) pursued multiple career paths, including in the fields of photography and real estate. She was born in Poughkeepsie, NY, and in her childhood moved with her family to New York City. She attended Bard College, graduating in 1967 with a degree in psychology. By this time, Hopp had already developed an interest in photography and in the late 1960s and early 1970s traveled the world to live and develop her craft as a "personal editorial documentary photographer."
Returning to New York in the 1970s, Hopp found a patron and mentor in Seymour Durst, the real estate developer. Durst employed her to photograph areas of New York City of interest to him from the standpoint of potential development targets. Perceiving the potential for, even the inevitability of, drastic change in the built environment of the areas she was assigned to photograph, Hopp expanded on the work to encompass a "photographic documentary art project." While initially satisfying Durst's needs for information, Hopp went well beyond that to preserve visually the buildings and streetscapes at the center of the tension between preservation and progress.
Hopp's work in this regard focused in substantial part on the midtown Manhattan area centered on Times Square and 42nd Street, an area that by the late 1970s had become a disreputable site known for pornographic movie houses, peep shows, and the like. Hopp's work documented the state, often deteriorated, of the buildings and the efforts through the 1980s and 1990s to renovate or demolish them. Hopp's work also included views from along the Hudson River waterfront (the site of a proposed elevated Westway Highway, which was never built) and from lower Manhattan along 6th Avenue (also known as Avenue of the Americas), as well as other locales. Many of these photographs were exhibited by Hopp or included as documentary illustrations in books, and came to be referred to in whole by Hopp as her New York City Archive. Seeking to place the material with a New York institution, Hopp donated the work in 2017 to the New-York Historical Society.
(The above was based in large part on an interview Maggie Hopp gave in 2015 to the on-line magazine, Ragazine.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
The bulk of the collection was a gift of the photographer, Maggie Hopp, in September 2017. Hopp donated her pictorial work "Great Aunt Belle" in July 2021.
Separated Materials Note
The donor included a copy of Anne Pasternak's catalogue Creative Time: The Book, edited by Ruth A. Peltason, published by Princeton Architectural Press, 2007. Maggie Hopp contributed photographs to this catalogue. The book was separated from the photographs for item cataloging and is shelved separately in N-YHS's Library.
Forty-second Street (New York, N.Y.); Manhattan (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Times Square (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Motion picture theaters.; Older women -- United States -- Pictorial works.; Photographers.; Real estate development.; Waterfronts -- New York (State) -- New York.; Photographs.; Durst, Seymour B., 1913-1995
- Waterfront (8x10, b&w), 1995-1996, undated (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents Note
  Includes about 123 photographs.
- Waterfront (8x10, b&w), 1995, 1996, undated (Box 2)
  Includes about 117 photographs.
- Waterfront Portfolio (11x14, b&w), 1996 (Box 16)
  Includes about 33 photographs.
- Waterfront (11x14, b&w), 1996, 1998 (Box 17)
  Includes about 104 photographs.
- Waterfront (11x14, b&w), [1996] (Box 18)
  Includes about 98 photographs.
- Waterfront (20x24, b&w), 1997, undated (Box 26)
  Includes about 31 photographs.
- Waterfront (contact sheets, b&w), 1975-1999, undated (Box 7)
  Includes about 93 sheets.
- Waterfront; Land & Development Sites (slides, mostly color), 1978-1996, undated (Box 9)
  About 53 sheets of color slides including, among others, 6th Ave (between 14th-30th streets) (1981); Westside Highway (1978); Waterfront (including slides for Hopp's exhibition On the Waterfront (1984, 1988, 1995-1996), including b&w slides for prints; land sites for Westside Highway (1982, 1987); Chelsea Piers/Waterfront/Hudson Guild Centennial (1995); Waterfront/Blizzard (1996); 42nd Street (1978).
- Waterfront (35mm negatives), 1975-1999, undated (Box 10)
  About 90 sleeves of 35mm negatives including, among others: Westside Highway/Waterfront (1978); Waterfront & General Theological Seminary (1999?); Waterfront (1984, 1995-99); Waterfront at 42nd Street (1997); Waterfront at 23rd Street and Battery Park City (1998); Waterfront/Homeless pier/bikeway (1995); Riverside South (1991); Fulton Landing (1984); Robert Fulton (boat)/South Street (1975).
- Outer Smut (16x20, color), 1999 (Box 23)
  Includes 23 photographs of exterior views from the Times Square/42nd street area, primarily of theater marquees, signage, and storefronts, with a principal focus on venues offering sexually pornographic movies, live nude shows, and other sex industry services. Identifiable venues include Terminal Bar, Adonis Theater, Fascination game arcade, Metropole Cafe, Pussycat, French Quarters, Frisco Theater (showing the movies "Deep Throat" and "Devil in Miss Jones"), Follies Burlesk (Gaiety male theater), Avon Theater, Girls to Dance, Jay Bee Magazines, Venus, Eros I and Screw theaters, Capri Theater, Girls Galore Burlesque, Maxie's Monogrammed Hats (selling tee shirts and sweatshirts), and a costume shop. The 1999 date is from the photographer's copyright on the back of each print, but the photographs were likely taken before then (e.g., the Adonis theater was demolished in 1995.) Many of these images can be found on-line at https://dangerousminds.net/comments/sleazy_city_amazing_pics_of_times_square_back_before_they_took_all_the_porn.
- Outer Smut (16x20, color), 1999 (Box 24)
  Includes about 107 prints, mostly multiple copies of photographs found in above box, except for one additional image, that of the Las Vegas theater.
- Theaters Under Siege. 42nd Street Theaters. Apollo, New Amsterdam, Lyric, Times Square, Liberty (8x10, b&w), 1989-1990, undated (Box 3)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes about 244 photographs of exteriors and interiors of the theaters, showing deterioration, demolition/gutting, decorative details, signage. A caption on two prints of the New Amsterdam roof top theater gives a short history of the theater and indicates that 16 of Hopp's photographs of the New Amsterdam were on display at the Municipal Art Society in 1990. Some photographs are captioned to show before and after work, such as sign removal at the Lyric.
- Theaters [Under Siege]. Victory, Selwyn, Empire, Harris (8x10, b&w), 1989, 1990, 1999, undated (Box 4)
  Includes about 157 photographs of exteriors and interiors of the theaters, showing deterioration, demolition/gutting, decorative details, signage. Includes before and after photographs of renovations at the Victory, including its marquee at the 1990 opening of "Crowbar." Includes some photos of the New Victory (1999). Includes photos of painted advertisements on buildings related to 42nd street as a destination for moviegoers.
- Theaters Under Siege (42nd Street Theaters) (11x14, b&w), 1989-1994 (Box 19)
  Includes about 130 photographs of theaters. Includes close-ups of building features, including those of the Harris, Lyric, Victory, Times Square, Empire theaters. Images of interiors, often deteriorated, including Liberty, Victory, Times Square, Empire, Selwyn theaters. Images of demolition of the Apollo Theater.
- Theaters Under Siege (42nd Street Theaters) (11x14, b&w), 1989-1994 (Box 20)
  About 46 photographs, including Images of dressing room, Empire Theater ceiling, interiors of theaters, including Academy/New Apollo bar, Times Square, Victory, Selwyn, Empire theaters.
- Theaters Under Siege (42nd Street Theaters) (11x14, b&w), 1990, 1991, undated (Box 21)
  Includes about 72 photographs. Images of demolition of theater interiors, including New Amsterdam and Empire theaters. Images of dressing room at the Victory Theater. Includes an inventory of the 11x14 prints of the New Amsterdam and "Theaters Under Siege" series.
- [Theaters Under Siege] New Amsterdam Theater (11x14, b&w), 1990, 1991, undated (Box 22)
  About 15 photographs.
- Theaters Under Siege (42nd Street Theaters). (16x20, b&w), 1989-1994 (Box 25)
  Includes about 46 photographs. Includes Victory Theater, Harris Theater, Lyric Theater, Times Square Theater (including marquee conveying the statement "A New Decade, A New 42 Street"), Apollo Theater, Liberty Theater (sign removal), New Amsterdam marquee, and Empire Theater. Includes wide angle views of north and south sides of 42nd street, birds-eye views, street/pedestrian/traffic views, and details of marquees, building decorative elements (e.g. urns atop Times Square Theater), deterioration, and boarded-up (closed) theaters.
- Theaters Under Siege (42nd Street Theaters) (20x24, b&w), 1989-1994 (Box 27)
  Includes 7 photographs.
- [Theaters Under Siege], Creative Time/42nd Street Art Project. Dupes & Originals. (slides, color and b&w), 1989-1994 (Box 12)
  Includes about 67 sheets of slides. Includes b&w slides of Theaters Under Siege photographs; color slides of New Amsterdam Theater exhibition at the Municipal Art Society (1990); color slides of Creative Time/42nd Street Art Project (1993).
- Creative Time/42nd Street Art Project (5x7, b&w, some color), 1993-1994 (Box 28, Case 1)
  Includes about 129 sheets of slides, a few in color, bulk in b&w. Images include the different artworks from the 42nd Street Art Project.
- 42nd Street Theaters (8x10, b&w), 1988-2010, undated (Box 5)
  Includes about 104 photographs. Includes some theaters, including Henry Miller's Theater/Shout, Victory Theater (demolition), and Lyric, Harem, Harris, and Apollo theaters. In addition to theaters, the box holds other views from the midtown/42nd street area. These include birds-eye views, street-length views, and specific buildings. Buildings include The Town Hall, Hotel Diplomat, Westside Theater playing Mamet's "The Cryptogram," The Actors Studio, The New Dramatists, Richards store, corner of 46th street & 5th avenue, Nathan's, corner of 42nd street & Times Square, corner of 42nd & 6th, New York Newsday building, and Tudor City. There are also photographs of a protest by the Times Square Preservation Committee and of street performers dancing. A small number of construction-related photographs date from 2010.
- 42nd Street (contact sheets, b&w), 1978-2000, undated (Box 8)
  Includes about 183 35mm contact sheets for images ranging from 1978 to about 2000. These include photographs related to the destruction or renovation of various theaters and other buildings in the Times Square/42nd street area. Many of the sheets include the prints found in earlier boxes, but there are many more images here, notably from the mid to late 1990s depicting demolitions and construction, including the collapse of the Selwyn (1997). These sheets also include photographs of those individuals with interests in the area, including governors George Pataki and Mario Cuomo, developer Seymour Durst, and protestors demonstrating against the changes (1990 Times Square rally). Many of the sheets include captions and dates on the reverse. Photographs other than theaters include Bryant Park, the Diplomat Hotel, New Years Eve 2000, #4 Times Square, Debt Clock (1999), and construction sites at the corner of 42nd street & 7th avenue and on 8th Avenue between 42nd and 43rd. There are some inventories, notes, a 9 page project description and some contact sheets for the Creative Time/42nd Street Art Project, and miscellaneous photos of unidentified individuals.
- 42nd Street (35mm negatives), 1978-2000, undated (Box 11)
  Includes about 183 sheets of negatives. Includes, among others, 42nd Street area buildings, demolition, construction (1978-1999), Debt Clock (1999), 6th Avenue in the area of street numbered in the 20s (1980s), #4 Times Square (1996-99), Durst buildings, New Years Eve Day in Times Square (1998-99), "Dawn of the Dead" on 42nd Street (1979), Diplomat Hotel (1990), Seymour Durst and Bryant Park (1987), theaters (Victory, New Victory, New Amsterdam, Ford Center), George Pataki luncheon (1995), Times Square rally (1990). Includes a few 8x10 negatives of theater-themed photographs.
- Protest of Durst Times Square Development (5x7, b&w), 1990-1996 (Box 28, Case 2)
  About 84 photographs. Includes Victory Theater, Governor George Pataki, Governor Cuomo, protest of destruction of New Amsterdam Theater, 1990 Earth Day, "Subsidize Arts not Office Towers" protest signs.
- Creative Time/42nd Street Art Project 1994; Misc.; Outer Smut; Waterfront. Dupes. (slides, color and b&w), 1978-1999 (Box 13)
  Includes about 37 sheets of slides. Includes color slides of Outer Smut, "Goddess" by Alex and Allyson Grey at Lincoln Center (August 1989), and 42nd Street Art Project (1994); and b&w slides of Theaters Under Siege and Waterfront.
- Buildings (8x10, b&w), 1987-1990, undated (Box 28, Folder 1)
  Includes various Durst buildings in New York City. Many images are duplicates.
- Durst's Negatives & Contact Sheets (5 folders), 1980-1994 (Box 28, Folder 2-6)
  includes about 72 sheets. Includes Seymour Durst, Windows on 6th Avenue, 1155 6th Avenue Building, 51st & 3rd Avenue excavation, 43rd & 5th Avenue, Hotel 123, Biltmore Hotel, 47th & 5th Avenue building under construction, Durst Buildings, Bryant Park (1987), Debt Clock (1992), parking lots at 43rd & 9th Avenue, 574 5th Avenue, "Cinderella Wore Combat Boots." Contact sheets for the Luxor Baths (1986). 8 negative and contact sheets of "Homeless in Carl Schurz Park" (1982), George Pissaro Studio and Gallery (1987), Lanny Power's City Lights sculpture (1989). 13 negative and contact sheets of Alexander, Anita, and Helena Durst, 1992 Earth Day Bryant Park/Durst Family, Debt Clock, 4 Times Square.
- [Various Subjects]: Luxor Baths, Durst, Debt Clock, 42nd Street Art Project (8x10, color and b&w), 1986-1997, undated (Box 6)
  Includes about 212 photographs. Includes, among others, color and b&w prints of Luxor Baths (1986) and b&w prints of Durst family (1990s), Debt Clock, John Ahern's project for Creative Time (1993), "Guys and Dolls" marquee and signage at Martin Beck Theater, Lanny Powers's City Lights sculpture. Many of the images are duplicates. Most 8x10, some 5x7.
- [Various Subjects] (slides, color), 1977-1998, undated (Box 14)
  Includes 18 color slide sheets of "Outer Smut," 9 color slide sheets of midtown area work (Penn Station, Rockefeller Center, Majestic Theater, Algonquin, Hotel 123), 23 color slide sheets of 42nd Street theaters, 4 Times Square, 42nd Street, 114 W. 47th Street, Larry Powers's City Lights sculpture (1988), lower 6th Avenue zoning (1981).
- [Various Subjects] (slides, color), 1977-1995 (Box 15)
  Includes, among others, 51 color slide sheets of westside undeveloped sites, which includes lowlying buildings (1981-1984), Rossoffs Bank, U.S. Steel Trust, Luxor Baths Hotel, lower 6th Avenue (1981), Debt Clock, Durst buildings, Durst family, 42nd Street (1977-78), Love Theater (1978), Hotel 123, Royal Manhattan Hotel (1978), Don Quixote sculpture (1984).
- [Inventories], 1990, undated (Box 28, Folder 7)
  Includes informal lists of images, number of prints, codes tying the images to negatives, and other rough notes.
- [Street Map of Lower 6th Avenue/Avenue of the Americas], undated (Box 28, Folder 8)
- "Great Aunt Belle, May 16, 1881-October 24, 1989", 2020 (Box 28, Folder 9)
  Hopp's self-published 2020 book of photos and text concerning her elderly Aunt Belle. Signed by Hopp. Photos taken mostly from 1988-89, in the last years of Aunt Belle's life.